Finding Aid for Wilbur Emery Hammaker Papers, 1947-1965
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Wilbur Emery Hammaker papers, 1947-1965
Hammaker, Wilbur Emery, 1876-1968
1 linear ft.
851388 Aa 2
Bishop of the Methodist Episcopal Church and temperance advocate. Speeches and articles and papers from his work with the National Temperance and Prohibition Council.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Dr. Paul M. Hammaker (donor no. 4936 ) and came to the library in 1970.
The collection is open to research.
Wilbur E. Hammaker was born February 17, 1876 in Springfield, Ohio. He pastored different churches in Ohio then in 1936 he was elected a bishop of the Methodist Episcopal Church. He then served in Nanking, China (1936-1939), in the Denver area (1939), and other assignments 1940 to 1948 when he retired. Bishop Hammaker was a leader within the church's temperance movement, serving as president of the Methodist Church Board of Temperance (1944-1948); then vice president in charge of counseling and public relations (1948-1952). He also served as president of the National Temperance and Prohibition Council (1948-1958). He died August 11, 1968.
The collection is arranged into three series, each primarily relating to the topic of temperance and the Methodist Church's advocacy of temperance. The series are Speeches, articles, and other writings; National Temperance and Prohibition Council; and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Clergy--Michigan.; Hammaker, Wilbur Emery, 1876-1968.; Methodist Episcopal Church.; Methodist Church (U.S.). General Board of Temperance.; National Temperance and Prohibition Council.; Prohibition--United States.; Social reformers--Michigan.; Temperance--United States.
Contributors:
Hooton, Caradine Ray, 1895-
- Speeches, articles, and other writings
  - Undated and 1947-January 1953, 12 folders (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of Drinking -- Is it Wrong? 1949 (Box 1)
  - "The History and Philosophy of the Temperance Movement" undated (Box 1)
  - Speeches of Deets Pickett, undated (Box 1)
  - Speeches of other temperance advocates (Box 1)
- National Temperance and Prohibition Council
  - Papers, 1942-1965, 11 folders (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Temperance organizations (general), 1950-1952, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Caradine R. Hooton papers, 1951-1965, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (Hooton was General Secretary of the General Board of Temperance of the Methodist Church)
  - Temperance pamphlets, 1944-1965 (Box 1)